God put you in a family to prepare you
for an ending. You submit
to nourish
and to cherish.
And in it
is wrapped
the love of Christ
which is sacrificial.
And the respect
for the husband.
And the love for the wife
which makes the place work in order.
And becomes a model
of a Christian home. Submit, nourish,
and cherish. Let me say it again, then
we say it together. Submit, nourish, and
cherish. Let's say it together.
We're going to say it with some energy,
right? If you are online, I want you
just say it to your screen. Say it.
Provide it once you are not in a place
that people will they will run away if
you are not in the office. Mhm? Even if
you are in a a restaurant, you can still
say
All right? Let's go. Submit, nourish,
and cherish.
Let's turn to the scripture, Ephesians
chapter 5 verse 21 to 33, New Living
Translation. We're going to read It's
going to be a long read, but make sure
you're paying attention.
Ephesians 5:21, it says, "And further,
submit to one another
out of reverence for Christ.
For wives, this means submit to your
husbands as to the Lord.
It says, "For a husband is the head of
his wife as Christ is the head of the
church.
He's the savior of his body, the church.
As the church submits to Christ, so you
wives should submit to your husbands in
everything.
For husbands, this means love your wives
just as Christ loved the church. He gave
up his life for her.
>> [snorts]
>> To make her holy and clean, washed by
the cleansing of God's word.
He did this to present her to himself as
a glorious church without a spot or
wrinkle or any other blemish. Instead,
she will be holy without fault.
In the same way husbands ought to love
their wives as they love their own
bodies. For a man who loves his wife
actually shows love for himself.
No one hates his own body, but
feeds and cares for it just as Christ
cares for the church.
And we are members of his body.
As the scripture says, a man leaves his
father and mother and be joined to his
wife and the two are united in one.
This is a great mystery, but it is an
illustration of the way Christ and the
church are one.
So again I say, each man
must love his wife
as he loves himself.
And the wife
must respect
her husband. That ends the reading of
the word.
Thank you.
>> [laughter]
>> Now that's the scripture. I want to say
this clearly this evening, what we are
discussing
we're discussing it from the Christian
perspective
and what the Bible says.
So it may not agree
with some of the popular sayings around.
Is either we are Christians or we are
not. Glory to God.
So, we have to choose
to be God rather than man.
So, you see from that scripture that the
Apostle
was trying to point something out
to the church
in Ephesus.
Apostle Paul uses the relationship
between Jesus Christ and the church as
an illustration
of what a Christian marriage
should be.
He sets the way Christ and the church
relates as a model
to follow.
Remember I said the title for the
message is what?
Submit
and cherish.
And I dare to say that these three words
will enhance
a good marriage.
Will help you as a believer
to enjoy your marriage.
Remember our theme is
marriage,
singlehood,
and self-control.
In other words, if you are not married,
don't excuse yourself because this is
where it starts.
There's nothing you do in marriage that
you probably Well, don't let me not say
there's nothing. It is what you learned
or who you are as a single person that
you take into marriage.
Good.
So, these three key words
the Apostle Paul looked at uses the
analogy of the relationship between
Christ and the church
which makes things work well
and uses it to explain how we should
behave in marriage if we want to enjoy
it.
So, let's start with the first word,
submit. I told you that we are going to
discuss.
Are you ready?
Because that word did not fall from
heaven.
It's a word
that we use every day.
Okay, so I'm going to ask question and I
want us to answer. May I request Pastor
Pastor Tim that you help me come with
one microphone close by anybody that
wants to answer. Just raise your hand.
Is that good?
Uh-huh.
>> [laughter]
>> Don't be afraid. It's not job question.
So, to you, what does it mean to submit?
Yes? Submit, yeah? Who wants to answer?
Quickly, quickly.
Let me have from two ladies, two guys,
or so. Whether you are married or you're
not married. Go ahead.
Yes.
Hallelujah.
>> To submit means to willingly leave,
respect, to cooperate, or to honor.
>> To willingly respect,
cooperate
>> and support.
>> And support. Let's put our hands
together for her.
Thank you.
Okay, who else want to say something?
There's someone in front here.
Here. Their hand is up here. Yes, sir.
>> In church.
>> Thank you.
>> to submit simply means to relinquish
control.
>> To relinquish control. Control, thank
you. Let's appreciate him. To relinquish
control. Listen very carefully, we are
not just doing this, okay, as a talk
show. I want you to pay at get those
words, okay? Yes, he's saying something.
Yes.
That Yes, the lady. Yes, please.
>> So, submit means to fully surrender.
>> To fully surrender. Thank you. One more.
Yes, so we've had two ladies and we had
two guys now. Yes.
>> [laughter]
>> Praise the Lord.
Uh I'm quoting a man of God.
He said you're what?
Okay, just say what your own answer is.
>> [laughter]
>> He said to submit means to arrange
yourself,
package yourself
under somebody,
a man specifically, who will be ready
to give his life
for you
before he will give for himself, the way
Christ gave to the church.
>> [laughter]
>> To package yourself and hand you over to
a man who will be willing to give
himself for you before for himself, just
the way Christ gave. Let's put our hands
together.
Okay. Thank you.
Good. So, to relinquish control.
What did the lady say here?
Willingly
surrender.
Good.
Okay, so
I'm sure you've picked something from
those
definitions.
They are actually correct.
I just want to add to it.
It means to defer.
Okay? Willingly cooperate.
Support. The lady mentioned support,
yeah?
Right.
Respecting order and responsibility in
the relationship.
It means choosing unity rather than
what? Rivalry.
I said it means to lay aside your
agenda,
your pride,
and your ego.
Praise the Lord.
That's what I consider as submit. And
the Apostle Paul
says,
wives should do what? Submit.
Now, before then, the first verse we
read, which is verse 21, says,
"Submitting yourselves one
to another."
And if you pay attention to the
definition that the other brother said,
you say you should package yourself
to a person, a basically a man who is
willing to give himself,
I mean, die for you, Abby, before for
himself. Good.
All right.
So, I said you have to lay aside your
agenda, your pride, and your ego.
Mhm.
And your ego. Yesterday,
we were at our staff devotion, and I I
threw this same question.
And somebody
who
is a data
person, used data language,
I mean, IT language to explain. He said,
"When you fill a form, right?
You then get to the end point and click
what? Submit. And the thing goes."
>> [laughter]
>> Then another person said,
"When you finish writing an exam
or a test, what do you do?
You submit without knowing who will mark
it."
Now, that tells that tells or talks
about some level of vulnerability.
That's being vulnerable.
Okay?
So,
let's continue.
So, I said, "In involving laying aside
your agenda." One of our pastors
yesterday said,
"It is you can break the word submission
into two. It says sub and mission."
I say you should put your own mission
under the main mission.
Is that making some sense?
>> [laughter]
>> Praise God.
Now, we're trying to break this down
because
I'm sure you've heard stories sometime a
couple
have been together 30 years
and then they say we no do again.
In other words,
it is no respecter of anointing.
Are you hearing me?
It is no respecter of your being in
church.
So, it's good if we can discuss so we
can help ourselves.
Praise God.
You lay aside your agenda, your ego,
your pride.
And as I was preparing, a scripture
quickly came to my mind and I want us to
read it.
In 1 John chapter
No, St. John's gospel chapter 13 verse 4
to 15.
In that place, Jesus laid aside his
garment. Let's look at this. So, he got
up from the table, took off his robe,
wrapped a towel around his waist.
And poured water into a basin, then he
began to wash the disciples' feet,
drying them with a towel and he had
around him.
When Jesus came to Simon Peter, Peter
said to him, "Lord, are you going to
wash my feet?"
Jesus replied, "You don't understand now
what I'm doing, but someday you will."
"No," Peter protested, "you will never
ever wash my feet." Jesus replied,
"Unless I wash you, you won't belong to
me."
Simon Peter exclaimed, "Then wash my
hands, my head as well, Lord, not just
my feet."
Jesus replied, "A person who has
bathed all over does not need to wash
except for the feet
to be entirely clean, and you and you
disciples are clean, but not all of
you."
>> [laughter]
>> But Jesus knew who would betray him.
That is what he meant when he said, "Not
all of you."
After washing their feet, he put on his
robe again and sat down and asked, "Do
you understand what I was doing?
You call me teacher and Lord, and you
are right because that's what I am.
And since I, your Lord and teacher, have
washed your feet, you ought to wash each
other's feet. Praise God.
Now, if you were talking about the the
church as at that time,
that was the core of the church. We'll
come back to the place of nourishing.
But what I just want to bring out
from there is that the first of those
verses,
he put aside his garment.
If you must submit, if you will be able
to submit, you will have to put aside
your ego.
In fact, there's another scripture that
I will want to read that talks about him
leaving. He did not consider himself
equal with God. He made himself of no
reputation.
So, just like one of the definitions
that says that you package and willingly
surrender yourself to someone who is
willing to die for you first
or willing to give himself for you first
before for himself.
Praise God.
So, it entails
laying aside
your ego.
Laying aside your agenda. It involves
cooperation.
All right? The decision to cooperate.
Choosing unity rather than rivalry.
That's what submit. So, you submit your
idea.
You decide let's work together.
I wish to quickly please say this.
And I want you to note it.
To submit does not mean to be
subservient.
Are we together?
It does not mean to be subservient. It
doesn't mean that you are lower
than the other person
or that you are less human.
Neither does it imply domination.
Because many times the man always say,
"Woman submit. Wife submit."
"Submit. Bible says submit."
Did the Bible say submit?
Yes.
It says so.
But the implication was not dominate.
It didn't say march your head upon her.
It didn't say treat her like some trash.
It didn't say
the wife is less intelligent
or is a subhuman.
I want to put that out.
So, I say again that submission is the
act of giving up control,
obeying commands,
or deferring to the judgment or power of
another person
or group.
So, bear in mind that this is not an
opportunity to beat down
the other partner or spouse.
That's not what submission is about.
If you are in an organization
and somebody must take the lead. After
everybody has discussed,
you all of you will then submit to the
general discuss decision.
Are we together?
Because you want to cooperate.
Sometime that decision may not be very
palatable.
In fact, sometimes you are persuaded
that what you were talking about or or
the path you would have wanted to take
may yield better result.
But because you want the place to work,
you yield ground.
Glory to God.
So, I want us to read another scripture.
We'll read
scriptures tonight.
Then we'll talk. 1 Peter chapter 3 verse
1 to 7.
It says, "In the same way you wives must
accept the authority of your husbands.
Then, even if some refuse to obey the
good news,
your godly lives will speak to them
without any words. They will be won over
by observing your pure and reverent
lives.
Do not be concerned about the outward
beauty of fancy hairstyles, expensive
jewelry,
or beautiful clothes.
You should clothe yourself, it said,
with the beauty that comes from within,
the unfading beauty of a gentle and
quiet spirit, which is so precious to
God.
This is how the holy women of old made
themselves beautiful.
They put their trust in God and accepted
the authority of their husbands.
For instance, Sarah obeyed her husband
Abraham and called him her master.
You are her daughters when you do what
is right without fear of what your
husband might do.
In the same way, you husbands must give
honor to your wives.
Treat your wife with understanding as
you live together.
She may be weaker than you are, but she
is your equal partner in God's gift of
new life.
Treat her as you should, so your prayers
will not be hindered.
So, you see that in Christianity, the
gospel of Christ balances things out.
In fact, in the in the
cultural environment of Jesus' day, the
culture in which Jesus
grew up,
women were treated less.
But, Jesus kept standing for the women
because he wanted to go
counter-cultural.
That is why when they brought a woman
and said she was caught in adultery in
the very act,
in the very act,
with her serabi,
>> [laughter]
>> and Jesus said, "This one won't work."
Are you getting me?
He gave the right of place
to the women.
So, you see the apostle, they are
speaking
balanced the whole thing.
The willingness to yield control.
That's a major point
you need to get from there.
So, for you to be able to submit, it
requires trust. Write that down. It
requires what? Trust.
If you cannot trust a person's capacity
to lead you, you may not be able to
submit. Am I correct?
Mhm.
So, for instance,
you are not sure
that this car you want to enter,
the person knows how to drive. Will you
enter it?
Or if you wanted to fly somewhere and
then as you enter,
you hear the pilot say, "Ladies and
gentlemen, it's about time to take off.
I'm really sorry. I didn't fully
complete my driving school. In fact, I'm
not going to any driving school, but I
trust God. I trust God.
With God, all things are possible.
What will you do?
I imagine if Nigerians are inside that
kind of aircraft, there will be
commotion all over my head.
Some people will plead the blood of
Jesus.
Some will break the window.
Glory to God.
If you can't trust the person, it's
going to be difficult. So, it requires
trust. And if you look at the scripture
that we just read,
it says something about trust. In verse
5, it says, "This is how the holy women
of old made themselves beautiful. They
put their trust in God
and accepted the authority of their
husbands." So, in the first place,
they did it because they trusted God
that if this is what he expects us to
do, he's made a provision and we take
charge. Are we together?
There has to be trust. Now, the
implication also is that if you are the
man, if you are not trustworthy, if you
want to demand for trust, you must be
what?
You have to be trustworthy.
That's why the Apostle Paul kept
balancing
the equation.
It requires trust. So, if you have trust
issues, you need to ask God to help you
tonight.
Because it's going to be difficult. You
know, there are some people they find it
difficult to yield control.
And so, they are suspicious. And this
doesn't have to do with just the ladies.
There are some
guys, they cannot trust anybody. You're
not going to be able to succeed in
marriage without trust.
So, you're going to have to
ask God to help you. And this model
or this is a model
for the married
and the single.
So, as a single person, if you cannot
submit
to the authority of your parents,
if you cannot submit to the authority of
your colleagues,
mark the word colleagues, right? So, for
instance, there are times that
you are in a project team or you're
asked
to
work together, right?
with others.
They are not superior to you.
Because this is where you build the
character with which you enter marriage.
If you cannot submit to another person
leading
as an usher in an ushering group,
Where is my magic? Okay.
You know, ushers are my special friends
in this church.
I'm just using that.
Any other unit where you are in a
voluntary,
you know, group like that,
then you're going to find it difficult
to submit in marriage. There are some
people they must be preeminent.
They must be in charge. It must be their
own, um,
idea.
Some don't know how to step back. Some
ladies have problem in marriage because
they don't know how to step back and be
a baby girl.
Yes.
>> [laughter]
>> So, all you need to do that to bring out
that feminine side of you.
Now, listen carefully. Sometimes
circumstances
may have molded some
to be like that.
And I always love to empathize with that
situation.
And we must never trivialize
people who have gone through things
or circumstances that have made somebody
to be what he or she
should not be.
We only call attention to it so that you
can see it
and you can access the help of God.
Are we together?
Now, it is possible because you had to
fend for yourself from childhood.
You don't know how to receive help if
they want to help you.
It's part of it.
So, as a single person,
examine yourself and pay attention to
this. Am I able to submit
to the authority of my parents? Am I
able to submit to the authority of my
colleagues? Am I able to submit to my
boss in the office
even when I think I'm better than him?
You know, there are some times you can
know that you know more than this
person.
Yeah.
What you don't know is that there's a
reason that person is there that time.
And there's a reason you are where you
are at the moment.
At such point, how do you behave? That
is your test of character.
That is the test to build in you
certain qualities.
Will you supplant the person or do you
help the person to shine?
You must be able to submit
to the authority of your friends. If you
are not able to do any of that, then
you'll find it difficult
to submit in marriage.
In fact, if you are not how do you even
relate with your siblings? Because
a preacher once said that God put you in
a family to prepare you for an enemy.
Everything you will see outside, you
will see it at home.
Maybe not to the same degree.
If you will be a stingy person, it will
start from home.
And when they ask you to share with your
brother
they don't.
And if I see a guy at home and you say
why should a guy wash plate?
May God help you if you are not a
disaster going somewhere to happen.
If you treat women, your sisters at home
as if they are trash,
you will do it outside.
But God help you. I used to warn guys
these days.
God help you cuz what your mother took,
the ladies will not take from you today.
May you not learn the hard way.
Okay, so this issue of submission starts
with a mindset.
What did I say?
And I want you to note that down. It
starts with a mindset and an attitude of
humility,
of yieldedness, and
an attitude that seeks cooperation
instead of
competition or rivalry.
That's where it starts. Philippians
chapter 2:5-8 New Living Translation
says, "You must have the same attitude
that Christ had.
Though he was God, he did not think of
equality with God as something to cling
to. Instead, he gave up his divine
privileges.
He took the humble position of slave and
was born as a human being."
When he appeared in human form, he
humbled himself in obedience to God and
died a criminal's death on the cross.
So, you see the example again. It starts
with an attitude, a mindset. Why should
I submit?
A whole me?
It's a If you If you can't If If you are
not willing to seek cooperation,
to lay aside some of your glory,
your pride, it will be difficult
to submit. So, I say it starts with
an attitude,
a mindset,
and an attitude of humility,
yieldedness, that seeks cooperation
instead of rivalry.
Now, that place ended up by saying he
died a criminal's death. We are not
asking you to die in a marriage. Are you
hearing
me? Uh-huh. And then, that's That's not
what we are calling submission.
Praise God.
Are you hearing me?
Thou shall not die
in the name of submission.
In case you think it's a joke, I'll give
you a story. One of those days, it was
it
>> [gasps]
>> One of those days, you know, we used to
hold four services on Sunday and we were
leaving service.
As I tried to drive out with my wife,
this lady ran and
what is it?
The husband has been beating her.
And she's pregnant.
I say, "Why? What?" I got
angry or surprised.
Okay. And she was coming from the police
station.
And that they said he should go back to
this church to her church
and report.
Uh-huh. So, what is it? She said she had
told a pastor, one of our pastors who is
no longer here. And that the pastor has
intervened. I say, "Okay. So, what
happened?"
He said the man didn't
obey and was still didn't, you know,
calm down and was still beating her.
When I heard that she was pregnant and
he's kicking her.
I don't want anybody to go out and say,
"Pastor, you was Pastor Solomon say I
should stay."
Therefore, they now kick her tummy and
she died.
I say, "You said which" She mentioned
the name of the pastor.
I said, "Well,
if you have reported to the pastor
and he will not listen, if he will not
obey our spiritual authority, he will
obey legal authority.
So, you go back
to the government authority.
I'm sure you will not like this one.
But I'm just illustrating it. So, as a
man, don't think you will use submission
don't want kill anybody. It's not
happening.
So, she went
and they picked him
and locked him.
I didn't say you should run to police
station and quickly do that.
They locked him.
And while he was there, I knew that he
will
not be able to come out. So, I spoke to
a lawyer to go and
and release him.
Praise God.
At least his head will calm down.
Because part of the problem is that the
wife said the guy say he likes me.
Mhm. You know how you like some pastor
you think the you know you are taking
after them, but I don't beat my wife
now.
>> [laughter]
>> So, you want to be spiritual you say you
resist the pastor you like and you beat
and you are going to kill her.
So, I sent to one of our legal people to
go and release
him.
So,
I was at home one of the counselors for
one of the units. Ah, the argument they
have brought their parents from outside
Lagos and they brought both of them to
my house.
When they got to a point
they were in my house till almost 12:00
midnight.
It was tough. So, as he what that was
talking, hey, she no one went and
arrested us. So, me and my wife told her
that we told her to go and arrest him.
Praise God.
I'm sure you don't like that. How can
pastor say that? See, if you will not
listen
to the spiritual authority
you will listen to legal authority.
You will not kill anybody on our head
here.
Praise God.
Well, so
and we told him the truth.
And even his mother cautioned, how do
you kick a woman that is pregnant.
Is that Christ?
There's no amount of spirituality that
can explain that.
That's carnality.
Even if you are speaking and fire is
coming out of your head.
Hallelujah.
So,
as much as possible,
submission should be out of mutual
or should be mutual and out of reverence
for Christ. Submission should be what?
That's what verse 21 says, that
submission should be mutual and out of
reverence for Christ.
So, we're going to answer another
question. Now, it's time to discuss
again.
The microphone. Where's the pastor?
So, why do people struggle with
submission?
Who is ready to answer?
Why do people struggle with submission?
Who wants to answer?
So, none of you struggle with
submission?
Yes.
Let's discuss.
Good evening, sir.
Are you hearing him?
Okay, can you
hear? Yes, good evening.
>> Yeah, I think sometimes lack of trust.
Um whenever you don't trust the leader,
many times it's very difficult to
submit. If you don't trust the vision
that our leader is portraying.
>> Lack of trust. Thank you, sir. Now, if
there is lack of trust, what should the
leader do?
No, be trustworthy.
>> [laughter]
>> Apart from that, the leader needs to be
vulnerable.
Are you Are you getting me?
Yes. You said lack of trust. Yes.
Another answer.
>> Yeah, also
I I think it's because the person
submitting has submitted again and again
and again and again and the person got
tired.
>> [laughter]
>> I'm not going to submit again.
>> You're not going to submit again. You
have submitted and submitted and
submitted and not submit again. It's
time for rebellion.
No, not rebellion. Thank you.
Thank you.
Now, we are taking white people
Okay, finding it difficult to submit. Is
someone learning something? So, if
someone is submitting to you, don't take
it for granted.
All right?
Good. One other reason? Any other
reason? Yes, ma'am.
Oh, yes, sir. Is this a woman? Yeah.
Okay, sir.
>> I think I also stand something.
>> Okay.
>> I remember one time I asked my
dad for an advice on a particular issue
that I needed to submit to my wife and
my dad was like, "Sheldon, you can't be
a soft man. You need to put your leg on
the ground."
And I said if I put my leg on the
ground, this one, my leg would break.
So, basically, I think it starts from
the home, too, you know.
>> Come on, let's put our hands together.
Thank you. Thank you. I was waiting for
that. Thank you. Yes. What else?
Yes, sir. So, what he's talking about is
cultural
mindset.
He says, "You are a man. Put your feet
down."
You know, as a man.
What Who else? Quickly, Quickly, because
we are running out of time.
Let's start with the Oh, you have people
at the back.
>> [laughter]
>> Okay, let's start with the lady. Start
with this lady here. Yes. Yes, ma'am.
You. Yes.
Start.
Our sound people, is there a microphone
very close to that place?
We will take one from there. Yes, ma'am.
>> Good evening, church.
>> Good evening, ma'am.
>> one of the reasons why we have problem
with submissions, misunderstanding.
>> Misunderstanding. Yes, explain a little
bit.
>> When we wait, the person that is
um to submit they don't understand the
mission of the person. Like in the
illustration given with Christ and the
disciples, can equally happen with us.
When you don't understand the mission
or the direction in which the leader is
going, you might decide not to submit.
Maybe with understanding, the person
might or might not submit.
>> Thank you. Thank you. Let's appreciate
her.
Misunderstanding.
You see, if you if you go back to 1
Peter chapter 3, it says, "Dwell with
them with what?"
So,
you need to clarify whatever you're
saying to your spouse.
Are we together?
It has to be clear. Don't just say
something and say this woman or this man
don't want to hear. You ask coconut
head.
Praise God.
Let's quickly take one from the back
there. Pastor Tunde, are you there with
them?
Who is with the microphone? Yeah? Just
one.
>> Praise the Lord.
>> Hallelujah.
>> From our um past experiences,
>> Mhm.
Can you explain a little?
>> Okay, so if people have been hurt
>> Mhm. and over again, there's a tendency
for them to be suspicious of
anybody. And so, when they there's a
defense that comes up. So, instead of
you to yield, you automatically
have that shield of
because you are afraid.
>> Thank you.
Let's appreciate her.
>> [applause]
>> Trauma and past experiences.
Listen, you see, that is why
when we get to the last two points, um
you will see the importance.
Trauma and past experiences.
You see, there are some people, the way
some words were used around them,
the connotation is such that once they
hear it,
something rises in them, a wall of
defense.
If they have ever used the word submit
as a means of oppressing you,
silencing you, torment you, when you
hear it,
oh, God,
a serious barrier will come up. In fact,
you will run or you are ready to fight.
The implication is that we need to pay
attention
to whoever we dealing with to find out.
And for a situation where somebody has
gone through such traumatic experience,
we have to be sensitive to them and seek
for help
for such person. Glory to God.
Okay, let me wrap up there so that we
can move
further.
Okay?
I hope I'm good.
Uh okay, I'm communicating with the
pastor over there. Okay.
All right. All right. Let's Let's
listen. Let's listen.
Wherever we get to and our time is up,
I'm sure we would have learned
something. Yes. Hello, ma'am.
>> One of the issues I could struggle with
is because in submission, you kind of
lose your
independence. So, you don't have the
ability to make decision. You need to
wait for someone to and decide for you
or give you a go ahead. Or you don't
have your voice anymore. So, I think
that's why people struggle for in
submission.
>> Thank you. Thank you. Let's appreciate
her, too.
You lose your independence. You lose
your voice.
See, so these are fears in our heart.
And we trust God to help us tonight
and throughout this series to deal with
them.
Because sometimes it delays you. What
that also say is that as a spouse, you
train yourself, be prepared also to act
swiftly and to I mean,
you you you need to, for instance,
assuage the person's fear.
They say you normally they will say let
the majority have their way, but the
minority should have their say.
Okay?
If um somebody is submitting to you,
and remember I said if somebody because
that scripture says submitting one to
another.
So, if your your wife is trying to
submit to you,
it means make sure you hear his her
voice.
Okay?
And if your husband is trying to submit
to you, make sure you hear her voice I
mean, his voice.
Look, the scripture we read about Sarah
said Sarah called Abraham Lord. Do you
remember?
But you remember the same Sarah was the
one that told Abraham,
"Go and sleep with them.
Eager.
And he obeyed.
Wait now. Why are you laughing like
this? Oh God.
>> [laughter]
>> And when after everything happened, he
start to blame Abraham. Say oh yeah,
send this woman away. Eh?
Abraham didn't want to God told him you
will be will listen to her because you
listen to her the other time.
I'm saying that even though she called
him Lord, Abraham didn't trample upon
her.
I hope you can see that.
He listened to her. So, what we are
hearing, I hope we can learn something
from When I do counseling, okay?
Both the things I learn from the the
complaint the couple are making,
especially the ladies, I also use it to
check my life.
Hello.
Because they complain their husband is
doing this. And somewhere somewhere,
maybe I do that. Yeah.
Wisdom tells me to repent quickly
before
my wife
will say, "This is my husband.
I don't know what he's doing."
Praise God.
So, we are learning together.
So, those are some of the challenges.
So, pay attention. You need to deal with
the cultural mindsets.
Okay? Somebody gave an illustration
about um a person that because she
started earning more and taking care of
most of the things in the house, I mean
the financial, she was earning more
anyway. I don't know whether she was
taking more care of most of the but
because she was earning in different
ways, it start she started feeling that
the husband could have actually also
stretched and earned in some other way.
So, she decided she was going to divorce
him.
Why? Because
from her cultural mindset, the man must
earn
more than the lady.
Let's be aware of cultural mindset.
Or a cultural mindset that say, "Don't
allow your wife to be to earn, no. He
will not She will not respect you again.
Therefore, you are caging her."
And you're not letting letting her
to make the best of her calling and her
ability. Praise God.
Are we gaining anything tonight? We are
not just telling stories.
We are learning together.
So, you see that ego sometimes also
contribute. Cultural mindset also
contribute. When I asked this question
among our staff, somebody said, "Culture
um um
entitlement mentality."
Entitlement
mentality.
You know, there are some of us that have
that entitlement, "You must do this for
me." And I was I asked the guys
yesterday. I said, "How many of you,
when you come back from work, expect
that your wife will have made food?"
Let me ask you now. If your wife is near
you, don't be ashamed. Even if he sees
you on TV on the online. Men, raise your
hand.
If when you come back Thank you, sir.
You will not raise it now. Me.
I used to expect it. Hello.
In fact, when I leave here now, I will
be expecting it.
Mhm.
Now, so those are expectations, right?
Is it bad to expect something?
It's not.
However, you must deal with a cultural
mindset that says, "Because she was at
home before you came, she was not She
was probably not as busy."
Right?
Because sometimes at home, the amount of
work
that the lady was doing,
the things she was thinking about.
You two went to work.
And she was working hard.
So, in my own case then, I expect the
food to have been served.
And sometimes my wife already has cooked
the food
and expect me go and get your food.
Hello.
I say sometimes. So, shame began to
catch me sometimes.
So, they will now say why you are
quarreling now is because of food.
Meanwhile, it's not as if the food was
not cooked.
And probably why it was not even served
is it might get cold.
Just carry yourself, pick it instead of
fighting
for no reason.
Is that wisdom?
>> [applause]
>> I know else men will not like me. I'm
not the one I'm just saying. I'm I
didn't say my own is the standard. I'm
telling you there are things to avoid.
So, don't let Satan enter
and cause trouble because of small
thing.
Praise God.
And sometimes you do the dishes, too.
And I used to tell people that some men
I say, "That's a nice way of saying say
you help me. Can you help me do the
dishes?"
I say I just imagine those days that our
mother that's cooking the pot on the
fire. And this side is equal to say go
and scrub the pot.
Now, you need to pay attention to the
fact that um
you know, the hormones,
if you are a guy, the hormones in the
man's body sometimes might make her not
to be in certain mood.
So, we must deal with cultural mindset
that say it is only a woman that must do
this. She's carrying the child. She's
doing this while you are sleeping,
snoring, carrying your leg or because
those things create unnecessary tension.
All right, let's move to the next two
points. Don't worry, this has summed up.
We have gone quite far.
The second thing is nourish.
Nourish. Paul says a husband should
nourish his wife the way he cares for
his own body. Hello.
You care for your body, right? If
something chokes your body, will you
like it?
You want to remove the pain, right?
So, to nourish means to provide tender
intentional care
that promotes growth
that brings flourishing and well-being.
So, it means to feed
your partner to develop, to strengthen
and to help that your partner
to do what?
To grow.
And this include giving emotional
support. You need to give your husband
or wife emotional support.
Okay?
You need to give that person. It
includes spiritual growth.
It includes
physical
care.
Physical care. Praise God.
Physical care.
Encouragement.
And protection.
Paul says that
Jesus nourishes and cherishes the body.
That's where I got the three words from,
submit, nourish, and cherish.
A nourishing husband helps his wife to
flourish, not shrink.
So you help her to think
when she has a challenge.
This my business that is disturbing me.
Not put the person that is a people like
you. There's some people they talk down
their spouses. And some women to their
own mouth can cut into pieces.
A nourishing husband creates an
environment where she can grow in
confidence, purpose, peace, and faith.
If you are married since
that lady got to your house, how much of
improvement has
she had?
You know, think about it.
The people you are in company of your
friends, are you putting them down or
are you nourishing?
That's where it starts from.
If you are not doing it as a single,
don't deceive yourself that you're going
to do it
as a married person.
There is need to be tender, forgiving
one another. Ephesians 4:32 says,
"Instead, be kind to each other." Some
people are too harsh in their words.
You beat down the self-esteem of your
wife or your husband or the people your
friends around.
It says, "Be kind to each other,
tenderhearted,
forgiving
one another just as God through Christ
did what?
Has forgiven you."
In marriage,
somebody said two married people married
people are two
fallible persons who have learned to
keep forgiving one another.
Because you will make mistakes. There's
no need to cut the other party down.
There is need to be tender
forgiving one another.
Now, we're talking about marriage
singleness and self-control, right?
Self-control involves putting your
emotion under.
Scripture says, be
angry, but sin not.
Just because your spouse offended you
and you want to get back at the person,
put yourself under control.
Oh, it's because she said so. That was
why I slapped her.
That's not self-control.
And if you are a guy and you used to you
are used to beating ladies, whether they
are your sisters or
or your friends around you, you are
likely going to be a violent husband.
This is a time to deal with it.
If we want to do it Christ's way.
Tell your neighbor, harshness must go.
Number three, cherish. Ephesians 5:29.
To cherish means to threaten I mean,
sorry, to treat one another as precious
and valuable. When you cherish
something, I I tell some ladies that you
are gold.
And everybody want gold, but not
everybody knows how to handle gold. Are
you aware of that?
So, be careful who you
hand yourself over to.
So, it means
that you should never
take each other for granted.
It means to value the person deeply. How
much do you value
your friends, your spouse?
It means to hold dear.
It means you need to to treat that
person tenderly. Jesus so much valued
the church that he would give his life
for them.
How much do you value
your spouse? And it doesn't have to be
in words.
It's in how you treat
her, how you speak to her.
Now, these words
That particular word carries warmth and
tenderness. And what Paul was saying is
that the husband should not merely
provide materially, but should treat his
wife
with gentleness, with honor,
and with affection.
To wrap up tonight,
I will encourage us
that we need to engage
the help of the Holy Spirit.
All that Paul spoke about is expected to
flow from our relationship with the Holy
Spirit.
If you see Same Ephesians 5:18 it says,
"Don't be drunk with wine
because that will ruin your life.
Instead,
be filled with the Holy Spirit."
Verse 19 says, "Singing psalms and hymns
and spiritual songs among yourselves and
making music to the Lord in your hearts
and giving thanks for everything to God
the Father in the name of Jesus Christ."
Then go to verse 21 and said,
and further
submit to one another
out of reverence for Christ. So, this
submission
would be an outflow
of the Holy Spirit working in you
when you are filled with him.
Because sometime I must tell you that
submission is not easy.
Do you agree with me?
So, it takes
if you if you find it difficult
you need to engage him.
There are times you need the Holy Spirit
to help you
to walk away.
You need to listen to him. Even though
Satan will tell you, "Is it you he's
talking to like that?"
And what could have just been resolved?
There I was a story of not long ago, I
think a year or two ago, where two two
people
fought and killed themselves.
In one of the states in the Southwest,
it was in the news.
And the children
had them They unfortunately they've
locked the door.
And they stabbed each other and they
both died.
If only one listened to the Holy Spirit
and walked away at that time. Just 5
minutes, 5 seconds.
And everything would have been saved.
So, you need to engage the Holy Spirit.
Galatians 5:22-23
says the Holy Spirit produces this kind
of fruit in our lives. Love, joy, peace,
patience, kindness, goodness,
faithfulness, gentleness, and what?
Self-control.
Allow him. You you need to engage him.
You need to engage him.
From time to time because he's the one
that will change your mind. Some of
these things we are calling cultural
mindset is not easy.
Because culture enters you when you
don't know.
Someone was saying yesterday that okay
that she wanted to ask a question that
uh whether some uh the person the person
ask him whether they will marry somebody
like
his mother.
Okay.
Or some ladies saying
they would don't want to marry someone
like their father. And we said
in many cases ladies marry someone like
their father.
And guys marry somebody like their
mother.
Yes, it happens many times.
Especially the ones that were angry at
what their their parents was doing and
almost hated the parent for doing that.
If you're not careful and intentional
you do that. So for instance you see
some guys when they are young, their dad
was a wife beater was beating their mom
and they hated him for that.
Yet
if they don't become very intentional
they will beat their own wife.
Because it has entered them
unconsciously.
But the help of the Holy Spirit
makes you to be able to overcome that.
So tonight as we close
I present to you
the three words
that the Apostle Paul
wrote there that will help us
to leave and enjoy a good marriage.
To submit
to nourish,
and to cherish.
And in it
is wrapped
the love of Christ
which is sacrificial.
And the respect
for the husband
and the love for the wife
which makes the place work in order
and becomes a model
of a Christian home.
Will you bow your head? Let's pray.
Can you just talk to God and ask God if
there is any pain in your heart, if
there is any challenge, any trauma that
you suffered, or
your marriage is in a state
whereby love seems to be
to be missing.
Or there is fight, constant fight,
disagreement.
One of the things the Holy Spirit
dropped in my heart is that he's going
to heal homes tonight. And as the word
was going on, his work was going on,
too.
So, can you ask God to heal your heart?
To heal your home.
If you're struggling with submission,
if you find yourself being harsh, if you
if you struggle with controlling your
temper,
can you talk to God and say, "Holy
Spirit, please help me."
Ask, "Holy Spirit, help me. Help me. I
need your help.
I need you. I need you. I want to enjoy
a good home. If you are not married,
you're single, can you talk to God,
develop these characters in me, and
prepare me for my future spouse?
I want to be able
to behave,
to act according to this model
that Christ and the church presents
before me.
Help me, Holy Spirit.
Help me, Holy Spirit. Just talk to him.
Just talk to him.
Ask him to bring peace.
Ask him to bring back joy.
And for that relationship that was on
the verge of collapse,
of breakdown, in the name of Jesus, I
pray
that the peace of God, which passes all
understanding, will flow through that
heart.
Let there be healing. Let there be
healing.
Let that trauma go in the name of Jesus.
Lord, send your peace. Whisper your
peace to every troubled heart, every
troubled home, every troubled marriage.
And for that person that grew in an
environment that it has affected you so
badly,
I pray for healing for you.
Let the healing hands of Jesus
touch you.
Precious Spirit, we give you praise. We
give you praise. We give you praise. We
give you praise. We give you praise.
Before I wrap up that prayer, I need
someone
that is honest tonight, want to enter
this relationship with Christ.
You know you're not born again. You are
not part of the body.
You're not part of the body, the bride
of Christ.
This is the time to say, "Jesus, come
into my heart.
I know I'm a sinner. Forgive me. Forgive
my sins and make me a new person." If
you are that person, wherever you are,
just place your right hand on your
chest.
And if you are in this physical
location, stand up on your feet just so
we identify you and pass on
things to you. If you are online, place
your right hand on your chest and just
say the prayer after me. Say, "Dear God,
I thank you
for sending your son to die for my sins.
I ask you to forgive my sins.
I receive you as my Lord and my savior
from tonight. I will live to please you.
I will live to please you.
In the name of Jesus. Father, I pray for
every such person that I prayed that
prayer. Let their sins be forgiven.
Write their names in the book of life
in the name of Jesus.
If you prayed that prayer, if you are
online, just click the link
in the chat room and leave us your
details. We want to keep praying for
you. We want to send you some material
that will help you to grow. Can everyone
just rise up on your feet this moment?
Just rise up on your feet. Just rise up
on your feet.
Precious Father, I pray for everyone in
this service.
I ask, oh God,
that you will heal every home
in the name of Jesus. Heal every
marriage
in the name of Jesus. Lord, remove
trauma from our our emotions. Heal us,
oh God. Let the thing that Satan has
planted a head to create crisis in our
home in the future. Let it dissolve in
the name of Jesus.
Lord, every single person trusting you
for a life partner connection.
Let bone come to bone in the name of
Jesus. Let every veil be removed.
Connect them to that person. Anyone that
suffered divorce and is trusting you, oh
God, I ask that you intervene
in the name of Jesus.
Lord,
restore.
Restore peace.
Restore joy.
Let your wisdom flow. Someone needs to
go back and say, "I am sorry."
Holy Spirit, help that person.
And as that person says, "I'm sorry,"
restore that home.
That person whose spouse walked away,
Father, bring them back.
Let
that joy they had from the beginning
that made them come together, let it be
restored.
We give you praise and glory.
For the children praying that God, can
you bring back our parents together?
Answer them.
To the glory and praise of your name. We
give you praise and glory. In Jesus'
mighty name we have prayed.
>> Daystar, raising role models.